funding for this program is provided by
additional funding provided by
today we turn to Kant's reply to
Aristotle Kant thinks that Aristotle
just made a mistake it's one thing Kant
says to support a fair framework of
Rights within which people can pursue
their own conceptions of the good life
it's something else and something that
runs the risk of coercion to base law or
principles of justice on any particular
conception of the good life
you remember Aristotle says in order to
investigate the ideal Constitution we
have first to figure out the best way to
live
Kant would reject that idea he says that
constitutions and laws and rights should
not embody or affirm or promote any
particular way of life that's at odds
with freedom for Aristotle the whole
point of law the purpose of the polis is
to shape character to cultivate the
virtue of citizens to inculcate Civic
excellence to make possible a good way
of life that's what he tells us in the
politics for Kant on the other hand the
purpose of law the point of a
constitution is not to inculcate or to
promote virtue its to set up a fair
framework of Rights within which
citizens may be free to pursue their own
conceptions of the good for themselves
so we see the difference in their
theories of justice we see the
difference in their account of law or
the role of a constitution the point of
politics and underlying these
differences are two different accounts
of what it means to be a free person for
Aristotle we're free insofar as we have
the capacity to realize our potential
that leads us to the question of fit fit
between persons and the roles that are
appropriate to them figuring out what
I'm cut out for that's what it means to
lead a free life to live up to my
potential Kant rejects that idea and
instead substitutes his famously
demanding notion of freedom as the
capacity to act autonomously freedom
means acting according to a law I give
myself freedom as autonomy part of the
the appeal part of the moral force of
the view of content of Rawls
consists in the conception of the person
as a free and independent self capable
of choosing his or her own ends the
image of the self is free and
independent offers up if you think about
it a powerful liberating vision because
what it says is that as free moral
persons we are not bound by any ties of
history or of tradition or of inherited
status that we haven't chosen for
ourselves and so we're unbound by any
moral ties prior to our choosing them
and that means that means that we are
free and independent sovereign selves
we're the authors of the only
obligations that constrain us the
communitarian critics of Kantian and
Rawls in liberalism acknowledge that
there is something powerful and
inspiring in that account of freedom
free independent choosing self but they
argue it misses something
it misses a whole dimension of moral
life and even political life it can't
make sense of our moral experience
because it can't account for certain
moral and political obligations that we
commonly recognize and even prize and
these include obligations of membership
loyalty solidarity and other moral ties
that may claim us for reasons that we
can't trace to an act of consent
alasdair macintyre gives an account but
he calls a narrative conception of the
cell it's a different account of the
self human beings are essentially
storytelling creatures MacIntyre argues
that means I can only answer the
question what am i to do if I can answer
the prior question of what story or
stories do I find myself apart that's
what he means by the narrative
conception of the self what does this
have to do with the idea of community in
belonging MacIntyre says this once you
accept this narrative aspect of moral
reflection you will notice that we can
never seek for the good or exercise the
virtues only as individuals we all
approach our circumstance as bearers of
particular social identities
I am someone's son or daughter a citizen
of this or that city I belong to this
plan that tried this nation
hence MacIntyre argues what is good for
me has to be the good for someone who
inhabits these roles I inherit from the
past of my family my city my tribe my
nation a variety of debts inheritances
expectations and obligations these
constitute the given of my life my
morale starting point this is in part
what gives my life its moral
particularity that's the narrative
conception of the self and it's a
conception that sees the self as claimed
or encumbered at least to some extent by
the history the tradition the
communities of which it's a part we
can't make sense of our lives not only
is a psychological matter but also as a
moral matter in thinking what we ought
to do without attending to these
features about us now MacIntyre
recognizes that this narrative account
this picture of the encumbered self puts
his account at odds with contemporary
liberalism and individualism from the
standpoint of individualism I am what I
myself choose to be
I'm a biologically be my father's son
but I can't be held responsible for what
he did unless I choose to assume such
responsibility I can't be held
responsible for what my country does or
has done unless I choose to assume such
responsibility but MacIntyre says this
reflects a certain kind of moral
shallowness even blindness it's a
blindness at odds with the full measure
of responsibility which sometimes he
says involves collective responsibility
or responsibilities that may float from
historic memories and he gives some
examples such individualism it's
expressed by those contemporary
Americans who deny any responsibility
for the effects of slavery upon black
Americans saying I never owned any
slaves or the young German who believes
that having been born after 1945 means
that what Nazis did to Jews has no moral
relevance to his relationship
to his Jewish contemporaries McIntyre
says all of these attitudes of
historical amnesia amount to a kind of
moral abdication once you see that who
we are and what it means to sort out our
obligations can't be separated shouldn't
be separated from the life histories
that define us
the contrast he says when the narrative
account is clear for the story of my
life is always embedded in the story of
those communities from which I derived
my identity I am born with the past and
to try to cut myself off from that past
is to deform my present relationships so
there you have in McIntyre a strong
statement of the idea that the self
can't be detached shouldn't be detached
from its particular ties of membership
history story narrative now I want to
get your reactions to the communitarian
critique of the individualist or the
voluntarist the unencumbered self but
let's make it concrete so that you can
react to more than just the theory of it
by looking at the two different accounts
of moral and political obligation that
arise depending on which of these
conceptions of the person one accepts on
the liberal conception moral and
political obligations arise in one of
two ways there are natural duties that
we owe human beings as such duties of
respect for persons Quay persons these
obligations are universal
then as Rawls points out there are also
voluntary obligations obligations that
we owe to particular others
insofar as we have agreed whether
through a promise or a deal or a
contract now the issue between the
liberal and communitarian accounts of
the self is there another category of
obligation or not the communitarian says
there is there is a third category that
might be called obligations of
solidarity or loyalty or membership the
communitarian argues that construing all
obligations as either natural duties or
voluntary obligations fails to capture
obligations of membership or solidarity
loyalties whose moral force consists
partly in the fact that living by them
is inseparable from understanding
ourselves as the particular persons we
are what would be some examples and then
I want to see how you would react to
them examples of obligations of
membership that are particular but don't
necessarily flowed from consent but
rather from membership narrative
community one situation the most common
examples are ones to do with the family
the relation between parents and
children for example suppose there were
two children drowning you could save
only one of them one was your child the
other was a stranger's child would you
have an obligation to flip a coin or
would there be something morally obtuse
if you didn't rush to save your child
now you may say well parents have agreed
to have their children so take the other
case the case of children's obligation
for their parents now we don't choose
our parents we don't even choose to have
parents
there is that asymmetry and yet
considered two aging parents one of them
yours the other strangers doesn't it
make moral sense to think that you have
a greater obligation to look after your
aged parent then to flip a coin or to
help the strangers now is this traceable
to consent not likely or take a couple
of political examples during World War
two French Resistance pilots flew
bombing raids over occupied France one
day one of the pilots received his
targets and noticed that the village he
was being asked to bomb was his home
village he refused not disputing that it
was as necessary as the target he bombed
yesterday he refused on the ground that
he couldn't bring himself it would be a
special moral crime for him to bomb his
people even in a cause that he supported
the cause of liberating France now do we
admire that if we do the communitarian
argues it's because we do recognize
obligations of solidarity take another
example some years ago there was a
famine in Ethiopia hundreds of thousands
of people were starving the Israeli
government organized an airlift to
rescue Ethiopian Jews they didn't have
the capacity to rescue everyone in
Ethiopia they rescued several hundred
Ethiopian Jews now what's your moral
assessment is that a kind of morally
troubling partiality a kind of prejudice
or as the Israeli government thought is
there a special obligation of solidarity
that this airlift properly
responded to well that takes us to the
broader question of patriotism
what morally speaking is to be said for
patriotism there are two towns named
Franklin one is Franklin Texas and the
other is just across the Rio Grande
River Franklin Mexico what is the moral
significance of national boundaries why
is it or is it the case that we as
Americans have a greater responsibility
for the health and the education in the
welfare and public provision for people
who live in Franklin Texas then equally
needy people just across the river
living in Franklin Mexico according to
the communitarian account membership
does matter
and the reason patriotism is at least
potentially a virtue is that it is an
expression of the obligations of
citizenship how many are sympathetic to
the idea that there is this third
category of obligation the obligation
obligations of solidarity or membership
how many are sympathetic to that idea
and how many are critical of that idea
how many think all obligations can be
accounted for in the first two ways all
right let's hear from the critics of the
communitarian idea first yes my biggest
concern with the idea of having
obligations because you're a member of
something or because of solidarity is
that it seems that if you accept those
obligations as being sort of morally
binding then there's a greater
occurrence of overlapping obligations a
greater occurrence of good versus good
and I don't know if this sort of
framework allows us to choose between
them
good in much your name
so you worried that if we recognize
obligations of membership or solidarity
since we inhabit different communities
their claims might conflict and what
would we do if we have competing
obligations yes
well one solution is that we could view
ourselves as ultimately members of the
human community and that then within
that we have all these smaller spheres
of that you know I am an American or I
am a student at Harvard and so the most
important community to be to be
obligated to is the community of human
beings and then from there you can sort
of evaluate which other ones are most
important to you so the most univer and
what's your name
Nikola so Nikola you say the most
universal community we inhabit the
community of humankind always takes
precedence yes Patrick are you satisfied
No
why not um it seems rather arbitrary
that we should choose the universal
obligation over the more specific
obligation I might also say that I
should be obligated first to the most
specific of my obligations for instance
take my family as a small unit of
solidarity perhaps I should be first
obligated to that unit and then perhaps
to the unit of my town and then my
country and then the human race good
thank you
let's I want to hear from another critic
of the communitarian view we have the
objection well what if Goods collide who
objects to the whole idea of it who sees
patriotism is just a kind of prejudice
that ideally we should overcome yes
patriotism reflects a community
membership that's a like a given I think
the problem is that
whereas some memberships are natural
narratives the narrative of citizenship
is a constructed one and I think a false
one because as the river is just a
historical accident it makes no sense
that because the lottery of birth threw
me into the United States as opposed to
Mexico that that's the membership that I
should be a part of good and what's your
name
Elizabeth Elizabeth who has a reply yes
I think in in general uh we have to ask
where do our moral obligations arise
from anyway and I think basically
there'd be two places from which they
could arise one would be kin another one
would be reciprocity and isn't the
closer you are associated to other
people there's a natural reciprocity
there in terms of having interactions
with those people you interact the
neighbors on your street with the other
people in your country through economic
arrangement I don't know and you don't
know those people in Franklin Texas any
more than you know the people in
Franklin Mexico do you presumably you're
naturally more connected with the people
in your own country in terms of
interaction and trade than you are with
people in other countries good
who else I'll go ahead yeah I think that
a lot of the basis for a patriotism can
be compared to like school spirit or
even house fear that we see here where
freshmen are sorted into houses and then
within a day they have developed some
sort of attachment or a pride associated
with that house and so I think that we
can probably draw a distinction between
a moral obligation for communitarian
beliefs and sort of just a sentimental
emotional attachment good way to say you
stay there what's your name
Rina what about go back to my example
about the obligation of the childhood
the parent would you say the same thing
there it's just a maybe or may not be a
sentimental toy but it has no moral
weight well I mean I'm not entirely
certain that accident
in the initial stage is something that
will preclude like moral obligations
later
and so you know just because we were
randomly sorted into a house or just
because we don't choose who our parents
are what country born into doesn't
necessarily mean that we won't like
develop an obligation based on some type
of benefit I guess just sort of see your
obligation to your parent that's greater
than two agent parents around the world
is only because and insofar as you're
repaying a benefit that your parent gave
you when you were growing up yeah I mean
I would say that if you look at cases of
adoption where you know you have a
biological parent somewhere else that
you don't interact with and then you
have a parent you know who adopted you
most people would say that if you had to
pick between them in the case of you
know aging parents that your obligation
would lie more with the person who
raised you and who had exchanges with
you meaningfully may ask you one more
question about the parent sure do you
think that a person with a bad parent
owes them less I don't know because I've
never had a bad parent I think that's a
good place to end thank you we'll
continue with this next time thank you
if I were working on an egg problem set
for example and I saw that my roommate
was cheating that might be a bad thing
for hoot for him to do but I wouldn't
turn him in you would not turn him in I
wouldn't turn him in and I think that I
would argue that's the right thing to do
because of my obligation um you know you
don't have a duty to tell the truth to
report someone who cheated today I'd
like to take I'd like to consider the
strongest objections to the idea that
there are obligations of solidarity or
membership then I want to see if those
objections can be met successfully one
objection emerged in the discussion last
time Patrick said well if obligations
flow from community membership and
identity we inhabit multiple communities
doesn't that mean that our obligations
will sometimes conflict so that's one
possible objection and then Rina said
these examples meant to bring out the
moral force of solidarity and membership
examples about parents and children
about the French resistance fighter
asked to bomb his own village in drawing
back about the airlift by Israel of
Ethiopian Jews these examples they may
be intuitively evocative Rina said but
really they're pointing to matters of
emotion matters of sentiment not true
moral obligations and then there were a
number of objections not necessarily to
patriotism as such but to patriotism
understood as an obligation of
solidarity and membership beyond consent
this objection
allowed that there can be obligations to
the communities we inhabit including
obligations of patriotism but this
objection argued that all of the
obligations of patriotism or of
community or membership are actually
based on liberal ideas and perfectly
compatible with them consent either
implicit or explicit or reciprocity
Julia rod how for example on the website
said that liberalism can endorse
patriotism as a voluntary moral
obligation patriotism and familial love
both fall under this category because
after all Julia points out the content
framework allows people free rein to
choose to express virtues such as these
if they want to so you don't need the
idea of a non-voluntary particular moral
obligation to capture the moral force of
community values where's Julia okay so
did I summarize that that fairly there
is action Julia actually is in line with
what Rawls says about this very topic
you weren't aware of that you came up
with it on your own that's pretty good
Rawls says when he's discussing
political obligation he says it's one
thing if someone runs for office or
enlist in the military they're making a
voluntary choice but Rawls says there is
I believe no political obligation
strictly speaking for citizens generally
because it's not clear what is the
requisite binding action and who has
performed it so Rawls acknowledges that
for ordinary citizens there is no
political obligation except insofar as
some particular citizen willingly
through an act of consent undertakes
or chooses such an obligation that's in
line with Julia's point it's related to
another objection that people have
raised which is it's perfectly possible
to recognize particular obligations to
one's family or to ins country provided
honoring those obligations doesn't
require you to violate any of the
natural duties or requirements of
Universal respect for persons quite
persons so that's consistent with the
idea that we can choose if we want to to
express a loyalty to our country or to
our people or to our family provided we
don't do any injustice within the
framework acknowledging the priority
that is of the universal duties the one
objection that I didn't mention is the
view of those who say that obligations
of membership really are a kind of
collective selfishness why should we
honor them isn't it just a kind of
prejudice so what I'd like to do
perhaps if those of you who have agreed
who wrote and who have agreed to defect
to press these objections perhaps if you
could gather down all together will form
a team as we did once before and we'll
see if you can respond to those who want
to defend patriotism conceived as a
communal obligation now there were a
number of people who argued in defense
of patriotism as the communitarian view
conceives it so let me go down now and
join the critics the critics of
communitarianism if there's a microphone
that we could use somewhere okay thanks
Kate who as the critics of patriotism
communal patriotism gather their forces
here Patrick if you want to you can join
as well arena and others who have spoken
or addressed this question are free to
join in
but I would like to hear now from those
of you who defend patriotism and defend
it as a moral obligation that can't be
translated back into purely
consent-based terms can't be translated
into liberal terms where's Ajay Kumar
Ajay everybody seems to know you all
right
let's hear from Ajay you said I in the
same way I feel I owe more to my family
than to the general community I owe more
to my country than to humanity in
general because my country holds a great
stake in my identity it is not prejudice
for me to love my country unless it is
prejudice for me to love my parents more
than somebody else's so Ajay what would
you say to this group stand up I think
that there's some fundamental moral
obligation that comes from a
communitarian responsibility to people
and groups that form your identity I
mean even like I'll give the example
that you know there are a lot of things
about our government right now that I'm
not in favor of but part of my identity
is that America value is a free society
where we can object to certain things
and I think that's an expression of
patriotism as well and I'd go back to
the parent example or even in Harvard I
think you know I owe more to my
roommates because they make up my Tenny
than I do to the Harvard community as a
whole and I think that applies to our
country because there are certain things
that growing up here yes we can't choose
if we can't choose our parents things
like that but it makes up part of our
identity okay who would like to take
that on hike yeah both the obligation to
others simply by virtue of being in
their their um being influenced by them
I'm a German citizen and if I had been
born 80 years earlier than I would have
been a citizen of Nazi Germany and for
some reason I just don't think that I
would have to feel obligated towards
Germany um because I benefited from
action
of Nazis I mean I guess my response to
that would be you have hundreds of
thousands of protestors the United
States right now who hold up signs that
say pieces patriotic and I'm sure there
are people in this room who don't agree
with that I personally do and I would
say that they're strongly objecting to
basically everything the Bush
administration is doing right now but
they still consider themselves loving
their country because they're furthering
the cause of what they see is best for
the country and I tend to agree with
that as a patriotic movement well but
how is that then how do you still favor
your country how is that so patriotic I
mean isn't that more sentimental
attachment where's the obligation
they're not to bring this back to John
Locke but I'd like to bring this back to
John Locke
so I mean in his conception of um you
know when people joined society there's
there's still some outlet like if you if
you're not satisfied with your society
you know you do have a means of exit
even though we had a lot of concerns
about how you're born and it's not very
feasible he still provides that option
if we want to say that your obligation
to society is a moral one that means
that prior to knowing exactly what that
society is going to be like or what your
position is going to be in that society
that means that you have a binding
obligation to like a complete unknown
body that that could be you know
completely foreign to all of your
personal beliefs or you know what you
would hope to be do you think that that
kind of communal obligation or
patriotism means writing the community a
a blank moral check basically yeah like
I think that we can you know I think
it's reasonable to say that as you grow
and as you develop within that community
that you acquire some type of obligation
based on reciprocity but to say that you
have a moral obligation I think requires
a stronger justification well anyone
else like to address that I guess we
could say that you you could argue that
you're morally obliged to society by the
fact that there is this reciprocity I
think it's the idea that you know we
participate in society we pay our taxes
we vote this is why we could say that we
owe something to society but beyond that
I don't think there's anything inherent
in the fact that we are members of the
society itself that we owe and anything
I think is insofar as we as the society
gives
something gives us protection safety
security then we owe the society
something but nothing beyond what we
give this assign who wants to take that
on Rahul I don't think we I don't think
we give the community a blank moral
check in that sense I think we only give
it a blank moral check when we abdicate
our sense of civic responsibility and
when we say that the debate doesn't
matter because patriotism is a vice I
think that patriotism is important
because it gives us a sense of community
a sense of common civic virtue that we
can engage in the issues even if you
don't agree with the way the government
is acting you can still love your
country and hate the way it's acting and
I think because out of that love of
country you can debate with other people
and have respect for their views but
still engaging in debate if you just say
that you know page 2 is a vice you drop
out of that debate and you and you see
the ground to people who are more
fundamentalist who have a stronger view
and who make worse the community it
instead we should engage the other
members of the community on that same
moral ground well now this what we hear
from a Jain Rahul is a very pluralistic
argumentative critically minded
patriotism whereas what we hear from
ICANN the critics of patriotism here is
the worry that to take patriotic
obligation in a communal way seriously
involves a kind of loyalty that doesn't
let us just pick and choose among the
beliefs or actions or or practices of
our country what more what's left of
loyalty if all we're talking about Ajay
and Rahul if all we're talking about is
loyalty to principles of justice that
may happen to be embodied in our
community or not as the case may be in
if not then we can can reject its course
I don't know I've sort of given a reply
I got carried away I'm sorry who liked
go ahead Julia yeah I think that
patriotism you needed to find what that
is it sounds like you know you would
normally think that we are given a more
weak definition here page which is
amongst us but it almost sounds like
your definition is merely to have some
sort of civic involvement in debating
within your society and I think that
that kind of undermines maybe the moral
some of the moral worth of patriotism as
a virtue as well I think if you can
consent to a stronger form of patriotism
if you want that's a stronger I guess
more obligation and even what you're
suggesting what we really need to
sharpen the issue is an example from the
defenders of communitarianism of a case
where loyalty can actually compete with
and possibly outweigh universal
principles of justice
isn't that what that's the test they
really need to meet isn't it all right
so that's the test you need to meet or
any any among you who would like to
defend obligations of membership or
solidarity independent of ones that
happen to embody just principles who has
an example of a kind of loyalty that can
and should compete with universal moral
claims respect for persons go ahead yeah
if I were working on an egg problem set
for example and I saw that my roommate
was cheating that might be a bad thing
for her for him to do but I wouldn't
turn him in you would not turn him in I
wouldn't turn him in and I think that I
would argue that's the right thing to do
because of my obligation him you know it
may be wrong but that's what I would do
and you know I think that's what most
people would do as well right that's now
there's a fair test he's not slipping
out by saying he's invoking in the name
of community some universal principles
of justice what's your name stay there
what's your name it's dan dan so what do
people think about Dan's case that's a
harder case for the ethic of loyalty
isn't it but a truer test how
I agree with Dan so loyalty Dan loyalty
has its part a sense it
how many disagree with Stan Peggy oh
well I agree with Dan but I agree that
it's a choice that we make but it's not
necessarily right or wrong I mean I'm
agreeing that I'm going to make the
wrong choice because I'm gonna choose my
roommate but I also recognize that
choice isn't morally right so you're
still translating even Dan's loyalty
you're saying well that's a matter of
choice but what's the right thing to do
the most people put up their hand saying
Dan would be right to stand by his
roommate and not turn him in let's go
ahead also I think as a roommate you
have insider information and that might
not be something you want to use that's
might be something unfair to hold
against you know you're spending that
much time with the roommate obviously
you're going to learn things about about
him and I don't think it's fair to
reveal that to a greater community but
it's loyalty Wojtek you you agree with
Dan that yes oil T is a ethic at stake
here absolutely you don't have a duty to
tell the truth to report someone who
cheated not if you're if you've been
advantaged into getting that kind of
information before our critics of
patriotism leave I want to give you
another version a more public example of
what will I guess we should call it
Dan's dilemma Dan's dilemma of loyalty
and I want to get the reaction of people
to this this came up a few years ago in
Massachusetts does anyone know who this
man is Billy Bulger that's right
who is Billy Bulger he was president the
Massachusetts state Senate for many
one of the most powerful politicians in
Massachusetts and then he became
president of the University of
Massachusetts now
Billy Bulger did you hear the story
about him that bears on Dan's dilemma
Billy Bulger has a brother named Whitey
Bulger and this is Whitey Bulger his
brother whitey is on the FBI's most
wanted list alleged to be a notorious
gang leader in Boston responsible for
many murders and now a fugitive from
justice but when when the US Attorney
they called Billy Bulger then the
president of the University of
Massachusetts before the grand jury and
wanted information on the whereabouts of
his brother this fugitive and he refused
to give it us attorney said just to be
clear mr. Bulger you feel more loyalty
to your brother than to the people of
the Commonwealth of Massachusetts and
here's what Billy Bulger said I never
thought of it that way but I do have a
loyalty to my brother I care about him I
hope that I'm never helpful to anyone
against him I don't have an obligation
to help anyone catch my brother and you
would agree how many would agree with
the position of Billy Bulger let me give
one other example and then we'll let the
critics reply the critics of loyalty as
we'll describe it here's a an even more
fateful example from a figure in
American history robert e lee now robert
e lee on the eve of the civil war was an
officer of the Union Army he opposed
secession in fact regarded as treason
when war loomed
Lincoln offered Lee to be the commanding
general of the Union Army and Lee
refused and he described in a letter to
his sons why he refused with all my
devotion to the Union he wrote I have
not been able to make up my mind to
raise my hand against my relatives my
children my home by which he meant
Virginia the Union is dissolved I shall
return to my native state and share the
miseries of my people save in her
defense I will draw my sword
no more here's a real test Dan for your
principle of loyalty because here is the
cause of the war against not only to
save the Union but against slavery and
Lee is going to fight for Virginia even
though he doesn't share the desire of
the southern states to secede now the
communitarian would say there is
something admirable in that whether or
not the decision was ultimately right
there's something admirable and the
communitarian would say we can't even
make sense
rina we can't make sense of Lee's
dilemma as a moral dilemma and thus we
acknowledge that the claim of loyalty
arising from his sense of narrative of
who he is is immoral not just
sentimental emotional tug all right who
would like to respond to Dan's loyalty
to Billy Bulger's loyalty or to robert e
lee's loyalty to virginia what do you
say it Julia okay well I think that this
is these are some classic examples of
you know multiple spheres of influence
and that you have conflicting
communities that your family in your
country I think that's one reason why
the idea of choice in your obligation is
so important because how else can you
resolve this you have if you're morally
obligated and there's no way out of this
need for loyalty to both communities
your tract there's nothing you can do
you have to make a choice
and I think that being able to choose
based on other characteristics than
merely you know the arbitrary fact that
you're a member of this community is
important otherwise it's left to use
randomness well Julia the issue isn't
whether these whether Dan makes a choice
or Billy Bulger or robert e lee of
course they make a choice the question
is on what grounds on what principle
should they choose the communitarian
doesn't deny that there's a choice to be
made the question is which choice on
what grounds and should loyalty as such
way Andre now you want to alright go
ahead what do you say why one of the
things we've noticed in the three
examples is that the people who've all
chosen the most immediate community of
which they're part the more local one
and I think there's something to be said
for that it's not just random they're
there I mean there doesn't seem to be
conflict because they know which one is
more important and it's their family
over the ak10 class their state over
their country and their family over the
Commonwealth of Massachusetts so I think
that's the answer to which is more
important you think that the local the
more particular is always the weightier
morally Andre well I mean there seems to
be a trend in the three cases I would
agree with that I think and I think most
of us would agree that your family takes
precedence over the United States
perhaps which is why you go with dan dan
loyalty to the roommate over act 10 and
the truth yeah exactly
I would because I mean I need
truth-telling not the truth of act n yes
all right so we understand yes but on
the same example in terms of family you
had cases in the civil war where brother
was pitted against brother on both sides
of the war where they chose country
instead of family so I think the exact
same more shows that different people
have different means of making these
choices and that there is no one set of
values or one set of morality that
communitarians can stick to and
personally I think that's the biggest
problem with communitarians
that we don't have one set of standard
moral obligations and tell me your name
Samantha so Samantha you agree with
Patrick Patrick's point the other day
that there may be if we allow
obligations to be defined by community
identification or membership they may
conflict there may they may overlap they
may compete and there is no clear
principled Andre says there's a clear
principle the most particular the other
day in Nicola who is sitting over here
whereas Nicola said the most universal
you're saying Samantha the scale of the
community as such can't be the decisive
moral factor so there has to be some
other moral judgement all right let's
first let's let our defence our critics
of communal patriotism let's express our
appreciation and thank them for their
having stood up and responded to these
arguments to find the issue let's turn
to the implications for justice of the
positions that we've heard discussed
here one of the worries underlying these
multiple objections to the idea of
loyalty or membership as having
independent moral weight is that it
seems to argue that there is no way of
finding principles of justice that are
detached from conceptions of the good
life as they may be lived in any
particular community suppose the
communitarian argument is right suppose
the priority of the right over the good
can't be sustained suppose instead the
justice and rights unavoidably are bound
up with conceptions of the good does
that mean
that justice is simply a creature of
convention of the values that happen to
prevail in any given community at any
given time one of the writings we have
among the communitarian critics is by
Michael Walzer he draws the implications
of justice this way justice is relative
to social meanings a given society is
just if it's substantive life has lived
in a certain way in a way that is
faithful to the shared understandings of
the members so Walters account seems to
bear out the worry that if we can't find
independent principles of justice
independent that is from conceptions of
the good that prevail in any given
community that we're simply left with
justice being a matter of fidelity or
faithfulness to the shared
understandings or values or conventions
that prevail in any given society at any
given time but is that an adequate way
of thinking about justice well let's
take a look at a short clip from the
documentary eyes on the prize goes back
in the 1950s in the south here are some
situated American Southerners who
believe in the tradition in the shared
understandings of segregation listen to
the arguments they make about loyalty
and tradition and see if they don't make
you uneasy about tying arguments about
justice to the shared understandings or
traditions that prevail in any given
society at the moment
it's from eclipse this land is composed
of two different cultures of white
culture and a colored culture and I live
close to them all my life but I'm told
now that we've mistreated them and that
we must change and these changes are
coming faster than I expected
and I'm required to make decisions on a
basis of a new way of thinking and it's
difficult difficult for me it's
difficult for all of them well there you
have it
narrative selves situated selves
invoking tradition doesn't that show us
that justice can't be tied to the shared
understandings of goods that prevail in
any given community at any given time or
is there a way of rescuing that claim
from this example think about that
question and we'll return to it next
time don't miss the chance to interact
online with other viewers of justice
join the conversation take a pop quiz
watch lectures you've missed and learn a
lot more
visit justiceharvard.org it's the right
thing to do
funding for this program is provided by
additional funding provided by