funding for this program is provided by
additional funding provided by
this is a course about justice and we
begin with a story
suppose you're the driver of a trolley
car and your trolley car is hurtling
down the track at 60 miles an hour
and at the end of the track you notice
five workers working on the track
you try to stop but you can't your
brakes don't work
you feel desperate because you know
that if you crash into these five
workers
they will all die
let's assume you know that for sure
and so you feel helpless
until you notice that there is
off to the right
a side track
and at the end of that track
there's one worker
working on the track
your steering wheel works
so you can
turn the trolley car if you want to
onto the side track
killing the one
but sparing the five
here's our first question
what's the right thing to do
what would you do let's take a poll
how many
would
turn the trolley car onto the side track
raise your hands
how many wouldn't how many would go
straight ahead
keep your hands up those of you who
would go straight ahead
a handful of people would the vast
majority would turn
let's hear first
now we need to begin to investigate the
reasons why you think
it's the right thing to do let's begin
with those in the majority who would
turn
to go onto the side track why would you
do it
what would be your reason
who's willing to volunteer
a reason
go ahead stand up um because it it can't
be right to kill five people when you
can only kill one person instead
it wouldn't be right to kill five
if you could kill one person instead
that's a good reason
who else does everybody agree with that
reason
go ahead
um well i was thinking it was the same
reason on
9 11 we regard the people who who flew
the plane into the
pennsylvania field as heroes because
they chose to kill the people in the
plane and not kill more people in
big buildings
so the principle there was the same on 9
11. it's a tragic circumstance but
better to kill one and so that five can
live
is that the reason most of you had those
of you who would turn yes
let's hear now from
those in the minority
those who wouldn't turn
yes well uh i think that's the same type
of mentality that justifies genocide and
totalitarianism
in order to say save one type of race
you wipe out the other
so what would you do in this case you
would
to avoid
the horrors of genocide
you would crash into the five and kill
them
presumably yes
yeah
okay who else
that's a brave answer thank you
let's consider
another trolley car case
and see
whether
those of you in the majority
want to adhere to the principle
better that one should die so that five
should live this time you're not the
driver of the trolley car you're an
onlooker
you're standing on a bridge overlooking
a trolley car track
and down the track comes a trolley car
at the end of the track are five workers
the brakes don't work
the trolley car is about to careen into
the five and kill them
and now
you're not the driver
you really feel helpless
until you notice
standing next to you
leaning over
the bridge
is a very fat man
and
you could
give him
a shove
he would fall over the bridge
onto the track
right in the way
of the
trolley car
he would die but he would spare the five
now
how many would push
the fat man over the bridge raise your
hand
how many wouldn't
most people wouldn't
here's the obvious question
what became of the principle
better to save five lives even if it
means sacrificing one what became of the
principle that almost everyone endorsed
in the first case
i need to hear from someone who was in
the majority in both cases how do you
explain the difference between the two
yes
the second one i guess involves an
active choice of uh pushing the person
down which
um i guess the that person himself would
otherwise uh not have been involved in
this situation at all and so to
choose on his behalf i guess
to uh
involve him in something that he
otherwise would have escaped is
i guess more than what you have in the
first case where the three parties the
the driver and the the two sets of
workers are already i guess in the
situation
but the guy working the one on the track
off to the side
he didn't choose to sacrifice his life
any more than the fat man did did he
that's true but he was on the tracks and
you this guy was on the bridge
go ahead you can come back if you want
all right it's a hard question
all right you did well you did very well
it's a hard question
um
who else
can
find a way of reconciling
the reaction of the majority in these
two cases yes well i guess um in the
first case where you have the one worker
and the five
uh it's it's choice between those two
and you have to make a certain choice
and people are going to die because of
the trolley car not necessarily because
of your direct actions the trolley car
is a runway
thing and you're making a split second
choice
whereas pushing the fat man over is an
actual act of murder on your part
you have control over that whereas you
may not have control over the trolley
car
so i think it's a slightly different
situation
all right who has a reply is that is no
that's that's good who has a way
who wants to reply
is that a way out of this
um i don't think that's a very good
reason because you choose to it's either
way you have to choose who dies because
you either choose to turn and kill the
person which is an active conscious
thought to turn or you choose to push
the fat man over which is also an active
conscious action so either way you're
making a choice
do you want to reply
well i'm not really sure if that's the
case it just still seems kind of
different the act of actually
pushing someone over onto the tracks and
killing him you are actually killing him
yourself you're pushing him with your
own hands you're pushing him and that's
different
than steering something that is going to
cause death into another
you know it doesn't really sound right
saying it now no it's good i'm up here
that's good what's your name andrew
andrew let me ask you this question
andrew yes
suppose
standing on the bridge
next to the man i didn't have to push
him suppose he were standing over a trap
door that i could open by turning a
steering wheel like that
would you turn
for some reason that that still just
seems more wrong
right i mean
maybe if you accidentally like leaned
into the steering wheel or something
like that
but uh or or say that the cars is
hurtling towards a switch that will drop
the trap
um
then i could agree fair enough it still
seems
wrong in a way that it doesn't seem
wrong in the first case to turn you say
and in another way i mean in the first
situation you're involved directly with
the situation and the second one you're
an onlooker as well all right so you
have the choice of becoming involved or
not by pushing the fact that let's let's
forget for the moment about this case
that's good
uh let's imagine a different case this
time you're a doctor in an emergency
room
and six patients come to you
they've been in a terrible trolley car
wreck
five of them sustained moderate injuries
one is severely injured you could spend
all day
caring for the one severely injured
victim
but in that time the five would die or
you could look after the five restore
them to health but during that time the
one severely injured
person would die how many would save the
five
now is the doctor how many would save
the one
very few people just a handful of people
same reason i assume
one life versus five
now consider
another doctor case
this time you're a transplant surgeon
and you have five patients each in
desperate need
of an organ transplant in order to
survive
one needs a heart one a lung
one a kidney one a liver
and the fifth
a pancreas
and
you have no organ donors
you are about to
see them die
and then
it occurs to you
that in the next room
there's a healthy guy who came in for a
checkup
and he's
you like that
and he's he's taking a nap
you could go in very quietly
yank out the five organs that person
would die
but you could save the five
how many would do it
anyone
how many put your hands up if you would
do it
anyone in the balcony
you would
be careful don't lean over too much
what
uh how many wouldn't
all right
what do you say speak up in the balcony
you who would yank out the organs why
i'd actually like to explore slightly
alternate possibility of just taking the
one of the five who needs an organ who
dies first and using
therefore healthy organs to save the
other four
that's a pretty good idea
that's a great idea
except for the fact
that you just wrecked the philosophical
point
well let's step back from these stories
and these arguments
to notice a couple of things
about the way the arguments have begun
to unfold
certain
moral principles have already begun to
emerge
from the discussions we've had
and let's consider
what those moral principles
look like
the first moral principle that emerged
in the discussion
said
the right thing to do the moral thing to
do
depends on the consequences that will
result
from your action
at the end of the day
better that five should live
even if one must die
that's an example
of consequentialist
moral reasoning
consequentialist moral reasoning locates
morality in the consequences of an act
in the state of the world that will
result
from the thing you do
but then we went a little further we
considered those other cases
and people weren't so sure
about
consequentialist moral reasoning
when people hesitated
to push the fat man
over the bridge
or to yank out the organs of the
innocent patient
people gestured toward
reasons
having to do
with the intrinsic quality of the act
itself
consequences be what they may
people were reluctant
people thought it was just wrong
categorically wrong
to kill
a person an innocent person
even for the sake of saving five lives
at least people thought that in the
second
version of each story we considered
so
this points
to a second
categorical
way
of thinking about
moral reasoning categorical moral
reasoning locates morality in certain
absolute moral requirements certain
categorical duties and rights regardless
of the consequences
we're going to explore
in the days and weeks to come the
contrast between consequentialist and
categorical moral principles
the most influential
example of consequential moral reasoning
is utilitarianism a doctrine invented by
jeremy bentham the 18th century english
political philosopher
the most important
philosopher of categorical moral
reasoning
is the
18th century german philosopher immanuel
kant
so we will look at those two different
modes of moral reasoning
assess them and also consider others
if you look at the syllabus you'll
notice that we read a number of great
and famous books
books by aristotle
john locke
emmanuel kant john stuart mill and
others
you'll notice too from the syllabus that
we don't only read these books
we also
take up
contemporary political and legal
controversies that raise philosophical
questions
we will debate equality and inequality
affirmative action
free speech versus hate speech same-sex
marriage military conscription a range
of practical questions
why
not just to enliven these abstract and
distant books
but to make clear to bring out what's at
stake in our everyday lives including
our political lives
for philosophy
and so we will read these books
and we will debate these
issues and we'll see how each informs
and illuminates the other
this may sound appealing enough but here
i have to issue a warning
and the warning is this
to read these books
in this way
as an exercise in self-knowledge
to read them in this way carries certain
risks
risks that are both personal and
political
risks that every student of political
philosophy
has known
these risks spring from the fact
that philosophy
teaches us
and unsettles us
by confronting us with what we already
know
there's an irony
the difficulty of this course consists
in the fact that it teaches what you
already know
it works by taking
what we know from familiar unquestioned
settings
and making it strange
that's how those examples work worked
the hypotheticals with which we began
with their mix of playfulness and
sobriety
it's also how these philosophical books
work philosophy
estranges us
from the familiar
not by supplying new information
but by inviting and provoking
a new way of seeing
but and here's the risk
once
the familiar turns strange
it's never quite the same again
self-knowledge
is like lost innocence
however unsettling
you find it
it can never
be unthought
or unknown
what makes this enterprise difficult
but also riveting
is that moral and political philosophy
is a story
and you don't know where the story will
lead but what you do know
is that the story
is about you
those are the personal risks
now what of the political risks
one way of introducing a course like
this
would be to promise you
that by reading these books and debating
these issues you will become a better
more responsible citizen
you will examine the presuppositions of
public policy you will hone your
political judgment
you will become a more effective
participant in public affairs
but this would be a partial and
misleading promise
political philosophy for the most part
hasn't worked that way
you have to allow for the possibility
that political philosophy may make you a
worse citizen
rather than a better one
or at least a worse citizen
before it makes you
a better one
and that's because philosophy
is a distancing
even debilitating
activity
and you see this going back to socrates
there's a dialogue the gorgeous in which
one of socrates's friends
calocles tries to talk him out
of philosophizing
calculus tells socrates philosophy is a
pretty toy
if one indulges in it with moderation at
the right time of life but if one
pursues it further than one should it is
absolute
ruin
take my advice calocly says
abandon argument
learn the accomplishments of active life
take for your models not those people
who spend their time on these petty
quibbles
but those who have a good livelihood and
reputation and many other blessings
so calacles is really saying to philos
to socrates
quit philosophizing
get real go to business school
and calace did have a point
he had a point because philosophy
distances us from conventions from
established assumptions and from settled
beliefs those are the risks
personal and political and in the face
of these risks there is a characteristic
evasion
the name of the evasion is skepticism
it's the idea well it goes something
like this we didn't resolve once and for
all
either the cases or the principles we
were arguing when we began
and if aristotle and locke and kant and
mill haven't solved these questions
after all of these years
who are we to think
that we here in sanders theater over the
course of the semester can resolve
them and so maybe it's just a matter of
each person having his or her own
principles and there's nothing more to
be said about it no way of reasoning
that's the evasion the evasion of
skepticism to which i would offer the
following reply
it's true these questions have been
debated for a very long time
but the very fact that they have
recurred and persisted
may suggest
that though they're impossible in one
sense they're unavoidable in another
and the reason they're unavoidable
the reason they're inescapable is that
we live some answer
to these questions every day
so skepticism just throwing up your
hands and giving up on moral reflection
is no solution
immanuel kant
described very well the problem with
skepticism when he wrote skepticism is a
resting place for human reason where it
can reflect upon its dogmatic wanderings
but it is no dwelling place for
permanent settlement
simply to acquiesce in skepticism count
wrote can never suffice to overcome the
restlessness of reason
i've tried to suggest through these
stories and these arguments
some sense of the risks and temptations
of the perils and the possibilities i
would simply conclude by saying
that the aim of this course
is to awaken the restlessness of reason
and to see where it might lead thank you
very much
like in a situation that desperate you
have to do what you have to do to
survive um you have to do what you have
to do you got to do what you got to do
pretty much if you've been going 19 days
without any food um you know someone
just has to take the sacrifice someone
has to make a sacrifice and people can
survive all right that's good what's
your name marcus marcus what do you say
to marcus
last time
we started out last time
with some stories
with some moral dilemmas
about trolley cars
and about doctors
and healthy patients vulnerable
to being victims of organ
transplantation
we noticed two things
about the arguments we had
one had to do with the way we were
arguing
we began with our judgments in
particular cases
we tried to articulate the reasons or
the principles
lying behind our judgments
and then confronted with a new case
we found ourselves re-examining those
principles
revising each in the light of the other
and we notice the built-in pressure to
try to bring into alignment
our judgments about particular cases
and the principles we would endorse on
reflection
we also noticed something about the
substance of the arguments
that emerged from the discussion
we noticed that sometimes we were
tempted to locate the morality of an act
and the consequences in the results in
the state of the world that it brought
about
and we call this consequentialist moral
reasoning
but we also noticed that in some cases
we weren't swayed only
by the result
sometimes
many of us felt
that not just consequences but also the
intrinsic quality or character of the
act
matters morally
some people argued that there are
certain things that are just
categorically wrong
even if they bring about a good result
even
if they save five people at the cost of
one life
so we contrasted consequentialists
moral principles
with categorical ones
today
and in the next few days we will begin
to examine one of the most
influential versions of consequentialist
moral theory
and that's the philosophy of
utilitarianism
jeremy bentham the 18th century english
political philosopher
gave first
the first clear systematic expression
to the utilitarian moral theory
and bentham's idea
his essential idea
is a very simple one
with a lot of
morally intuitive
appeal bentham's idea is
the following
the right thing to do
the just thing to do
is to maximize
utility what did he mean by utility
he meant by utility the balance
of
pleasure over pain
happiness over suffering
here's how he arrived at the principle
of maximizing utility
he started out by observing
that all of us
all human beings are governed by two
sovereign masters
pain and pleasure
we human beings
like pleasure and dislike pain
and so we should base morality
whether we're thinking about what to do
in our own lives
or whether
as legislators or citizens we're
thinking about what the laws should be
the right thing to do individually or
collectively
is to maximize act in a way that
maximizes the overall level of happiness
bentham's utilitarianism is sometimes
summed up with the slogan the greatest
good for the greatest number
with this
basic principle of utility on hand let's
begin to test it and to examine it by
turning to another case another story
but this time
not a hypothetical story
a real life story the case of the queen
versus dudley and stevens
this was a 19th century british law case
that's
famous
and much debated in law schools
here's what happened in the case
i'll summarize the story then i want to
hear
how you would rule
imagining that you are the jury
a newspaper account of the time
described the background
a sadder story of disaster at sea was
never told than that of the survivors of
the yacht mignonette
the ship foundered in the south atlantic
thirteen hundred miles from the cape
there were four in the crew
dudley was the captain
stevens was the first mate brooks was a
sailor
all men of excellent character or so the
newspaper account tells us
the fourth crew member was the cabin boy
richard parker
17 years old
he was an orphan
he had no family
and he was on his first long voyage at
sea
he went the news account tells us rather
against the advice of his friends
he went in the hopefulness of youthful
ambition
thinking the journey would make a man of
him
sadly it was not to be
the facts of the case were not in
dispute a wave hit the ship and the
mignonette went down
the four crew members escaped to a
lifeboat
the only
food they had were two
cans of preserved turnips no fresh water
for the first three days they ate
nothing
on the fourth day
they opened one of the cans of turnips
and ate it
the next day they caught a turtle
together with the other can of turnips
the turtle
enabled them to subsist for the next few
days and then for eight days
they had nothing no food no water
imagine yourself in a situation like
that
what would you do
here's what they did
by now the cabin boy parker is lying at
the bottom of the lifeboat in the corner
because he had drunk seawater against
the advice of the others
and he had become ill
and he appeared to be dying
so on the 19th day dudley the captain
suggested that they should all
have a lottery that they should draw
lots to see who would die
to save the rest
brooks refused
he didn't like the lottery idea
we don't know whether this was because
he didn't want to take the chance or
because he believed in categorical moral
principles
but in any case
no lots were
drawn the next day there was still no
ship in sight so dudley told brooks to
avert his gaze and he motioned to
stevens
that the boy parker had better be killed
dudley offered a prayer
he told the boy his time had come
and he killed him with a pen knife
stabbing him in the jugular vein
brooks emerged from his conscientious
objection to share in the gruesome
bounty
for four days the three of them fed on
the body and blood of the cabin boy
true story
and then they were rescued
dudley describes their rescue
in his diary
with staggering euphemism quote on the
24th day
as we were having our breakfast
a ship appeared at last
the three survivors were picked up by a
german ship they were taken back to
falmouth in england
where they were arrested and tried
brooks turned state's witness
dudley and stevens went to trial they
didn't dispute the facts
they claimed they had acted out of
necessity that was their defense they
argued in effect better that one should
die
so that three could survive
the prosecutor
wasn't swayed by that argument
he said murder is murder and so the case
went to trial now imagine you are the
jury
and just to simplify the discussion
put aside the question of law
and let's assume that you as the jury
are charged with deciding
whether what they did was morally
permissible or not
how many
would vote
not guilty that what they did was
morally permissible
and how many would vote guilty what they
did was morally wrong
a pretty sizable majority
now let's see what people's reasons are
and let me begin with those who are in
the minority
let's hear first from the defense
of dudley and stevens
why would you morally exonerate them
what are your
reasons yes
i think it's i think it is morally
reprehensible but i think that there's a
distinction between what's morally
reprehensible and what makes someone
legally accountable
in other words you know as the judge
said what's what's always moral isn't
necessarily against the law and while i
don't think that necessity
justifies
theft or murder or any illegal act at
some point your degree of necessity does
in fact exonerate you from any guilt
okay good other defenders other voices
for the
defense
moral justifications for
what they did yes
all right thank you um i just feel like
in a situation that desperate you have
to do what you have to do to survive um
you have to do what you have to do you
got to do what you got to do pretty much
if you've been going 19 days without any
food um you know someone just has to
take the sacrifice someone has to make
the sacrifice and and people can survive
and furthermore from that let's say they
survive and then they become productive
members of society who go home and start
like a million charity organizations and
this and that and this and that i mean
they benefit everybody in the end yeah
so i mean i don't know what they did
afterwards they might have gone and like
killed more people
whatever but what
what if they were went home and they
turned out to be assassins but if they
weren't going home and turned out to be
assassins
well you'd want to know who they
assassinated that's true too
that's good
that's fair okay
all right that's good what's your name
marquise marcus all right
we've heard a defense
a couple of voices for the defense now
we need to hear
from the prosecution most people think
what they did was wrong
why
yes
one of the first things that i was
thinking was oh if they haven't been
eating for a really long time maybe
they
that they're mentally like affected and
so then
that that could be used as a defense a
possible argument that oh
they weren't in the proper state of mind
they weren't making decisions they might
otherwise be making and if that's an
appealing argument that that you have to
be an altered mindset to do something
like that it suggests that
people who find that argument convincing
do you think that they were acting but i
want to know what you think you defend
them you vote i'm sorry you vote to to
convict right yeah i don't think that
they acted in a morally appropriate way
and why not what do you say here's
marcus he just defended them
he said
you heard what he said yes that that
yes
that you've got to do what you've got to
do in a case like that
yeah what do you say to marcus
that in
that there's no situation that would
allow human beings to take
the idea of fate or the other people's
lives in their own hands that we don't
have that kind of
power good okay thank you and what's
your name brett brett okay who else
what do you say
stand up i'm wondering if dudley and
steven had asked richard for richard
parker's consent
in you know dying um if that would
would that exonerate them from
from uh an act of murder and if so is
that still morally justifiable that's
interesting all right consent wait wait
hang on what's your name
kathleen kathleen says suppose they had
what would that scenario look like so
in the story dudley is there pen knife
in hand
but instead of the prayer
or before the prayer
he says
parker
would you mind
we're desperately
hungry as marcus empath
empathizes with we're desperately hungry
you're not going to last long anyhow
yeah you can be a martyr would you be a
martyr
how about it parker
then
then would it be what do you think would
it be morally justified then suppose
suppose parker in his semi-stupor says
okay
um i don't think it would be morally
justifiable but i'm wondering even then
even then it wouldn't be no you don't
think that even with consent
it would be morally justified are there
people who think
uh who want to take up kathleen's
consent idea and who think that that
would make it morally justified raise
your hand if it would if you think it
would
that's very interesting
why would consent
make a moral difference
why would it yes well i just think that
if he was making his own original idea
and it was his idea to start with then
that would be the only situation in
which i would
see it being appropriate in any way
because that way you couldn't make the
argument that he was pressured you know
it's three to one or whatever the ratio
was right and um i think that if he was
making a decision to give his life then
he took on the agency
to sacrifice himself which some people
might see as admirable and other people
might disagree with that decision
so if he came up with the idea
that's the only kind of consent we could
have confidence in
morally then it would be okay
otherwise
it would be kind of coerced consent
under the circumstances
you think
is there anyone who thinks
that even the consent of parker
would not justify
their killing him
who thinks that
yes tell us why stand up
i think that uh parker would be killed
with the hope that the other crew
members would be rescued so
there's no definite reason that he
should be killed because you don't know
who
when they're going to get rescued so if
you kill him it's killing him in vain do
you keep killing a crew member until
you're rescued and then you're left with
no one because someone's going to die
eventually well the moral logic of the
situation seems to be that
that they would
keep on picking off the weakest maybe
one by one
until they were
rescued and in this case luckily they
were rescued when three at least were
still alive
now if
if parker did give his consent
would it be all right do you think or
not no no it still wouldn't be right and
tell us why it wouldn't be all right
first of all cannibalism i believe is
morally incorrect
so you shouldn't be even human anyway so
you so cannibalism is morally
objectionable outside so then even on
the scenario
of waiting until someone died still it
would be objectionable yes to me
personally i feel like um
it all depends on one's personal morals
and like we can't sit here and just like
this is just my opinion and of course
other people are going to disagree but
we'll see let's see what their
disagreements are and then we'll see if
they have reasons that can persuade you
or not let's try that
all right let's um
now is there someone
who can explain those of you who are
tempted by consent
can you explain
why consent makes
such a moral difference what about the
lottery idea
does that count as consent remember at
the beginning
dudley proposed a lottery suppose that
they had agreed
to a lottery
then
how many would then say
it was all right suppose there were a
lottery
cabin boy lost
and the rest of the story unfolded then
how many people would say it was morally
permissible
so the numbers are rising if we add a
lottery let's hear from one of you for
whom the lottery would make a moral
difference
why would it
i think the essential element in my mind
that makes it a crime is
the idea that they decided at some point
that their lives were more important
than his and that
i mean that's kind of the basis for
really any crime right it's like
my needs my desires are more important
than yours and mine take precedence and
if they had done a lottery where
everyone consented that someone should
die
and it's sort of like they're all
sacrificing themselves to save the rest
then it would be all right
a little grotesque but
but morally permissible
yes
and what's your name matt
so matt for you
what bothers you is not the cannibalism
but the lack of due process
i guess you could say that
right
and can someone who agrees with matt
say a little bit more
about why a lottery
would make it in your view
morally permissible
go ahead
the way i understood it originally was
that that was the whole issue is that
the cabin boy was never consulted
about whether or not something was going
to happen to him even with the original
lottery whether or not he would be a
part of that it was just decided that he
was the one that was going to die right
that's what happened in the actual case
right but if there were a lottery and
they'd all agreed to the procedure
you think that would be okay right
because then everyone knows that there's
going to be a death whereas you know the
cabin we didn't know that this
discussion was even happening there was
no you know forewarning
for him to know that hey i may be the
one that's dying all right now suppose
he everyone agrees to the lottery they
have the lottery the cabin boy loses and
he changes his mind
you've already decided it's like a
verbal contract you can't go back on
that you've decided the decision was
made
you know if you know that you're dying
for the you know the reason for others
to live you would if someone else had
died you know that you would consume
them so
that's right
but but then he could say i know but i
lost
i just think that that's the whole moral
issue is that there was no consulting of
the cabin boy and that that's what makes
it the most
horrible is that he had no idea what was
even going on that had he known what was
going on it would
be a bit more understandable all right
good now i want to hear so there are
some who think
it's morally permissible but only about
twenty percent
uh
led by marcus
then there are some who say the real
problem here
is the lack of consent
whether the lack of consent to a lottery
to a fair procedure
or
kathleen's idea lack of consent at the
moment
of death
and if we add consent
then
more people are willing to consider
the sacrifice morally justified
i want to hear now finally from those of
you who think even with consent
even with the lottery
even with a final
murmur of consent by parker
at the
very last moment it would still
be wrong
and why would it be wrong that's what i
want to hear yes
well the whole time i've been leaning
all towards the categorical moral
reasoning
and i think that
there's a possibility i'd be okay with
the idea of a lottery and then the loser
taking into their own hands to
kill themselves
so there wouldn't be you know an act of
murder but i still think that
even that way it's coerced and also i
don't think that there is any remorse
like in dudley's diary we were eating
our breakfast it seems as though he's
just sort of like um
you know the whole idea of not valuing
someone else's life
so that makes me
feel like i have to take the category
you want to throw the book at him
when he lacks remorse or a sense of
having done anything wrong right
so all right good other any
other defenders of like
who say it's just categorically wrong
with or without consent yes stand up
why i think undoubtedly where society's
shape murders murder
murder is murder and in every way and
our society looks at murder down down on
it in the same light and i don't think
it's any different in any case good let
me ask you a question there were three
lives at stake
versus one okay
the one the cabin boy he had no family
he had no dependents these other three
had families back home in england they
had dependents they had wives and
children
think back to bentham
bentham says we have to consider the
welfare the utility the happiness of
everybody we have to add it all up
so it's not just numbers three against
one
it's also all of those people at home
in fact the london newspaper at the time
and popular opinion sympathized with
them
dudley and stevens and the paper said if
they weren't
motivated by affection and concern for
their loved ones at home and their
dependents surely they wouldn't have
done this yeah and how is that any
different from people on the corner
trying to have with the same desire to
feed their family i don't think it's any
different i think in any case if i'm
from murdering you to advance my status
that's murder and i think that we should
look at all that all in the same light
instead of criminalizing certain uh
activities and uh and and making certain
things seem more violent and savage when
in the same case it's all the same it's
all the same act and mentality that goes
in the murder necessity feeds your
family so suppose it weren't three
suppose it were thirty
three 300
one light to save 300.
or in wartime 3 000. suppose the stakes
are even bigger suppose it takes even
better i think it's still the same deal
do you think bentham is wrong to say the
right thing to do
is to add up the collective happiness
you think he's wrong about that i don't
think he's wrong but i think murder is
murder in any case well then bentham has
to be wrong if you're right he's wrong
okay and he's wrong all right
thank you well done
all right let's step back from this
discussion
and
notice
how many objections have we heard to
what they did
we heard some defenses of what they did
the defenses had to do with
necessity their dire circumstance and
implicitly at least the idea that
numbers matter
and not only numbers matter but the
wider effects matter their families back
home their dependents
parker was an orphan no one would miss
him
so if you
add up
if you tried to calculate the balance
of happiness and suffering
you might have a case for
saying what they did was the right thing
then we heard at least three different
types of objections
we heard an objection that said
what they did was categorically wrong
mike here at the end categorically wrong
murder is murder it's always wrong even
if
it increases the overall happiness
of society
a categorical objection
but we still need to investigate
why murder
is categorically wrong
is it because
even cabin boys have certain fundamental
rights
and if that's the reason
where do those rights come from if not
from some idea of the larger welfare or
utility or happiness question number one
others said
a lottery would make a difference a fair
procedure matt
said but
and some people were swayed by that
that's not a categorical objection
exactly
it's saying
everybody has to be counted as an equal
even though at the end of the day one
can be sacrificed
for the general welfare
that leaves us with another question to
investigate why does agreement to a
certain procedure
even a fair procedure
justify whatever result flows
from the operation of that procedure
question number two
and question number three
the basic idea of consent
kathleen got us onto this
if the cabin boy had agreed himself
and not under duress
as was added
then it would be all right to take his
life to save the rest
and even more people signed on to that
idea
but that raises
a third philosophical question what is
the moral work
that consent
does why does an act of consent
make such a moral difference
that an act that would be wrong taking a
life without consent
is morally permissible
with consent
to investigate those three questions
we're going to have to read some
philosophers
and starting next time
we're going to read bentham and john
stuart mill utilitarian philosophers
don't miss the chance to interact online
with other viewers of justice join the
conversation take a pop quiz watch
lectures you've missed and learn a lot
more visit justiceharvard.org it's the
right thing to do
funding for this program is provided by
additional funding provided by
you